<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>iopanic</title>
    <link>https://www.iopanic.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on iopanic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.iopanic.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Signing Coinbase Pro requests with Postman</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/coinbase_pro_hmac_postman/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/coinbase_pro_hmac_postman/</guid>
      <description>For running some tests against the GDAX/Coinbase Pro API, I needed to send properly signed requests with Postman. To achieve this, I&amp;rsquo;ve created the short pre-request script below that you can easily add to your Postman collection. More information about signing Coinbase Pro API messages can be found in their documentation.
You might want to adapt the variable names and URL path regex according to your needs. Also, don&amp;rsquo;t forget that you still need to set the proper headers in your request resource.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building and deploying docker images from Travis to ECR</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/deploying_to_ecr_from_travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/deploying_to_ecr_from_travis/</guid>
      <description>This article assumes that you&amp;rsquo;re generally familiar with Docker, Amazon IAM, Travis CI and some basic bash scripting.
I used to use Quay as a private registry but found that when heavily relying on AWS just using ECR gets the job done nicely and is a bit cheaper. However, AWS doesn&amp;rsquo;t give you a build environment like Quay does. So you have several options: Setting up your own, pushing images from the developer machine or simply using your already existing CI infrastructure to build and push your images.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five Hops To Hitler</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/five_hops_to_hitler/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/five_hops_to_hitler/</guid>
      <description>According to a friend, a common assumption exists, stating that almost no article on Wikipedia is more than five degrees separated from the article about Adolf Hitler. To verify this assumption, I have analyzed the German Wikipedia and computed the shortest distance between all vertices and the vertex representing the article about Adolf Hitler. The result shows that 97.1% of all articles have a path length of ≤ 5.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applied Curiosity</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/applied_curiosity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/applied_curiosity/</guid>
      <description>As a kid, you probably looked at things and often asked yourself: Why? Why does my water pistol transform this lazy thing called water into a pressurized stream I can aim at my cat? And why is my cat not enjoying the free shower? When we look at the physical world, we see amazing things all the time. Laws of nature are repeatable. Everything we do is based on the understanding that a natural law is applicable anywhere in our universe.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker development environments with Dusty</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/docker_dusty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/docker_dusty/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve seen hell, when it comes to software development and actual production environments. Inconsitent platforms, packages and a plethora of hacks to &amp;lsquo;get everything to work&amp;rsquo; on all developer machines. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen whole teams screwing with a shared &amp;lsquo;dev database&amp;rsquo; on a root server somewhere, creating a horrible mess of inconsistent behavior and ultimately slow down development and testing. This article will give you an overview how you can use Docker and Dusty to streamline your dev environments.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye ezeep!</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/goodbye_ezeep/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/goodbye_ezeep/</guid>
      <description>For all of you who haven’t noticed yet, I’ve left ezeep at the end of December. As a co-founder it’s been a tough decision to leave, after joining forces with my two amazing co-founders nearly three years ago. Looking back, building ezeep was an incredible and fun challenge.
However, I started to feel that the direction ezeep is moving into and my own passions were drifting apart and that someone else would be able to fulfill the changed requirements much better than me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nsync - A command-line tool for NSA’s backup services</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/nsync/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/nsync/</guid>
      <description>NSA is running the largest and most secure free backup service ever built. Still I couldn’t find any proper command-line backup tool to quickly compress and send my files to their service. So I’ve decided to introduce nsync:
nsync is an easy to use bash command-line tool to backup your files to NSA’s fully secure and free backup servers.
This is a very early version of nsync. Due to the robustness of NSA’s data collection and storage systems it should be very reliable though.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How XEROX Invented (and Killed) Printing</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/xerox_printing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/xerox_printing/</guid>
      <description>This article was originally published by me on the ezeep blog. Please note that ezeep, including it&amp;rsquo;s blog contents, has been acquired since then. Consequently this post might not appear on the ezeep blog anymore or might reference to a different author within ezeep&amp;rsquo;s new parent company.
Losing The Hackers In the late 1970’s, Richard Stallman and his colleagues at the MIT Artificial Intelligence Lab were using one of the first XEROX Xerographic printers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You’re Shaped By Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/shaped_by_algorithms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/shaped_by_algorithms/</guid>
      <description>Gaining Certainty Through Abstraction Technology has always shaped how we interact with the world and the people around us. Let’s start off with a very simple example: When the first bridges were built, the engineering part was a great achievement, but the idea of building a bridge is less about solving engineering problems just for the sake of solving them. Building a bridge is in it’s very essential core about connecting people.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Me. Commiting Code.</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/commiting_code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/commiting_code/</guid>
      <description>Cool, isn’t it? I stole the idea from Victor Martinez (http://coderwall.com/p/xlatfq) who fully deserves the credit for me annoying the web with this video.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You are too serious - Or why Germany still sucks for startups</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/you_are_too_serious/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/you_are_too_serious/</guid>
      <description>After a wild startup ride with Liquid Labs in Boston last year, I moved to Berlin recently and have joined ezeep as CTO. Right before I left Cambridge I gave a little seminar about the differences in European and US startup culture at MIT E-Club. An interesting discussion evolved in the seminar and finally I found some time to write a little post about the question why European startups (I will focus on Germany) still face trouble to form global market leaders like Facebook or Google.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Business Model Generation</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/post/business_model_generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/post/business_model_generation/</guid>
      <description>A few days ago Martin forwarded me an email about the book &amp;lsquo;Business Model Generation&amp;rsquo; by Alexander Osterwalder and Yves Pigneur. I checked out a preview of the book and quickly decided that it&amp;rsquo;s worth to give it a shot and to spend the 25 Euros. I haven&amp;rsquo;t regreted to do so.
What is the book about? &amp;lsquo;Business Model Generation&amp;rsquo; gives a structured overview about the single parts of a substantiated business model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marian Zange</title>
      <link>https://www.iopanic.com/page/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.iopanic.com/page/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Marian Zange, I’m a software consultant and engineer. My work is mostly focused on complex systems, infrastructure and managing software engineering organizations. Besides this, I&amp;rsquo;m co-founder of 5to3, a non-profit dedicated to improving the scientific process and the preservation and safeguarding of research data by bridging the gap between classical institutional trust models and decentralized systems.
Past companies I&amp;rsquo;ve co-founded include ezeep, a cloud printing service for education and businesses (acquired by ThinPrint) and Liquid Labs, a formerly Cambridge, MA based startup focused on natural language processing - primarily text summarization and clustering.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>