<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Software Engineering on iopanic</title>
    <link>http://www.iopanic.com/categories/software-engineering/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Software Engineering on iopanic</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.iopanic.com/categories/software-engineering/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Building and deploying docker images from Travis to ECR</title>
      <link>http://www.iopanic.com/post/deploying_to_ecr_from_travis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iopanic.com/post/deploying_to_ecr_from_travis/</guid>
      <description>This article assumes that you&amp;rsquo;re generally familiar with Docker, Amazon IAM, Travis CI and some basic bash scripting.
I used to use Quay as a private registry but found that when heavily relying on AWS just using ECR gets the job done nicely and is a bit cheaper. However, AWS doesn&amp;rsquo;t give you a build environment liek Quay does. So you have several options: Setting up your own, pushing images from the developer machine or simply using your already existing CI infrastructure to build and push your images.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Get your sh*t together: Docker development environments with Dusty</title>
      <link>http://www.iopanic.com/post/docker_dusty/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.iopanic.com/post/docker_dusty/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve seen hell, when it comes to software development and actual production environments. Inconsitent platforms, packages and a plethora of hacks to &amp;lsquo;get everything to work&amp;rsquo; on all developer machines. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen whole teams screwing with a shared &amp;lsquo;dev database&amp;rsquo; on a root server somewhere, creating a horrible mess of inconsistent behavior and ultimately slow down development and testing. This article will give you an overview how you can use Docker and Dusty to streamline your dev environments.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>